Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty (VADP); Records apap304
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty1937-2008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty
apap304
16.65 cubic ft.
This collection contains materials used by Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty (VADP) in its efforts to end capital punishment in Virginia.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of select items noted in Series 5.
Acquisition Information
Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty donated its records to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2008 July.
Biographical History
Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty was founded in 1991 under the name of Virginians for Alternatives to State Killing by a group of 13 concerned citizens. In 1994 they adopted their current name, Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty (VADP). The group seeks a moratorium on the death penalty in Virginia and to educate the public about inconsistencies in capital punishment.
The VADP rallies against the death penalty in a number of ways, including execution vigils, and practices only non-violent protests. The VADP holds yearly conferences that individuals can attend. Membership of the VADP is open to anyone who wishes to join and is not restricted to just Virginia citizens.
The VADP works to educate the public about the ineffectiveness of the death penalty in Virginia and Virginia's 21 day rule, a policy which prohibits trial judges from reviewing newly discovered evidence if it is presented more than three weeks after a defendant's sentencing. A moratorium on capital punishment in Virginia has been the group's goal for the past 25 years and remains so.
Scope and Contents
The Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty (VADP) Records cover 17 years of the organization's efforts to end the death penalty in Virginia. Materials included in this collection document the VADP's day-to-day activities and include petitions seeking an end to capital punishment in Virginia, Virginia General Assembly legislation, case law and legal education materials, subject files, newspaper clippings, scholarly articles, VHS tapes, and banners.
Although the VADP was established in 1991, a number of materials dated prior to 1991 are included in the collection, acquired by the VADP for research purposes.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 and 4 are arranged chronologically while Series 2,3, 5, 6, and 7 are alphabetical.
Death Penalty; Capital punishment--Virginia; Capital punishment--Moral and ethical aspects; Juvenile justice, Administration of--Virginia; Bills (legislative records); Files by subject; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Petitions; VHS; Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty
- Administration, 1988-2008; 1; 1.0 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of administrative materials of Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty including meeting minutes, calendars, and notes.
  - Lethal Injection Notes and Update, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Teleconference Notes and Materials, 1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Virginia General Assembly Questionnaire, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Meeting Materials, 1989-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Community Coordinators Roster, 1993; 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Meeting Notes, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - House of Delegates Survey, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - VADP 1999 Annual Conference (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - VADP Awards Banquet Booklet, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Receipts, 1999-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Death Penalty Contacts and Resources, 1999; 2006; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - VADP 10th Anniversary Banquet Preparation, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - VADP 10th Anniversary Banquet, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - VADP Members Who Donate to the Senate, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Vigil Permit, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Virginia General Assembly Questionnaire, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
  - NCADP Meeting Notes, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 17)
  - Notes, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Anti-Death Penalty Legislative Strategy, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Benefit Concert, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Book Signing, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Council of Churches, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 22)
  - Juvenile Death Penalty Talk Materials, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 23)
  - Lynchburg College Lecture Materials, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 24)
  - Membership Application and Donations, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 25)
  - Muhammad and Malvo Letter Writing Campaign, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 26)
  - VADP Awareness Day, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 27)
  - VADP Calendar of Events, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 28)
  - VADP Newsletter, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 29)
  - Notes, 2003; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 30)
  - Calendar, 2003-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 31)
  - Innocence Project Talk, 2003-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 32)
  - Grass Roots Meetings, 2003-2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 33)
  - ACLU Survey and Results, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 34)
  - Amnesty International Chapter Talk, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 35)
  - Death Penalty Working Group Conference Call, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 36)
  - Legislative Strategy Session, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 37)
  - Moratorium Organization Committee Conference Call, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 38)
  - Requests for Information, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 39)
  - Senator Cuccinelli Notes, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 40)
  - Students Against the Death Penalty, 2004; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 41)
  - VADP Abolition Day Tour, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 42)
  - VADP Accomplishments and Talking Points, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 43)
  - VADP Amicus Brief, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 44)
  - VADP Calendar with Notes, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 45)
  - VADP Conference, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 46)
  - VADP Fast and Vigil, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 47)
  - VADP Meetings, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 48)
  - Virginia People of Faith Meeting, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 49)
  - VADP Newsletter, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 50)
  - Write in, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 51)
  - Looth Execution, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 52)
  - Activity Updates, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 53)
  - E-File Index, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 54)
  - Faith Leaders Against the Looth Execution, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 55)
  - Lobby Day Agenda, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 56)
  - Newsletters, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 57)
  - VADP Activities Update, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 58)
  - VADP August Meeting, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 59)
  - VADP Juvenile Death Penalty Survey, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 60)
  - VAMC Minutes 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 61)
  - 85 Recommendations, 2005; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 62)
  - Moratorium Conference Call, 2005; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 63)
  - Promotional Materials, 2005-2006; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 64)
  - Conference Notes, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 65)
  - NCADP Conference Scholarship Application, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 66)
  - Moratorium Campaign Meeting, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 67)
  - Lethal Injection Conference Call, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 68)
  - The Journey of Hope, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 69)
  - VADP Director's Report, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 70)
  - VADP Equal Justice and Fair Play Press Release, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 71)
  - VADP Executive Board Meeting, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 72)
  - VADP March Meeting, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 73)
  - VADP Year in Review, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 74)
  - VAMC Tides Grant, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 75)
  - Volunteers List, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 76)
  - Legislative Strategy Session, 2006; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 77)
  - Statewide Community Organization Plan, 2006; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 78)
  - VAMC Meeting, 2006-2007; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 79)
  - Legislative Strategy, 2007 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 80)
  - Notes, 2007 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 81)
  - VADP Conference, 2007 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 82)
  - NCADP Ad Payment, 2008 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 83)
  - Conference Evaluation, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 84)
  - Contacts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 85)
  - Journey of Hope Thank You Draft, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 86)
  - Juvenile Death Penalty Efforts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 87)
  - List of Moratorium Enclosures, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 88)
  - Mailings Volunteers, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 89)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 90)
  - Press Contracts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 91)
  - Moratorium Organization Committee Members Roster, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 92)
  - VADP Assessment, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 93)
  - VADP Handouts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 94)
  - Virginia Moratorium Groups, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 95)
  - Virginia Newspapers Stance on the Death Penalty, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 96)
- Legal, 1984-2007; 2; 3.0 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series is comprised of case files, general assembly house and senate bills, and law journals used by Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty for legal research in their efforts to bring about a moratorium on capital punishment in Virginia.
  - 21 Day Rule, 2004-2005; Undated (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 1)
  - 21 Day Rule Proposed Amendment, 2003; Undated (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 2)
  - 1988 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 3)
  - 1988 Virginia General Assembly Lethal Injections (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 4)
  - 1990 Virginia General Assembly SB226 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 5)
  - 1991 Virginia General Assembly SB789 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 6)
  - 1998 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 7)
  - 1999 Virginia General Assembly, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 8)
  - 1999 Virginia General Assembly HB606 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 9)
  - 1999 Virginia General Assembly HB933 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 10)
  - 1999 Virginia General Assembly HB2298 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 11)
  - 2000 Virginia General Assembly HB1311 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 12)
  - 2001 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 13)
  - 2002 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 14)
  - 2003 Legislative Summaries (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 15)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly Capital Cases and Mental Retardation (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 16)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly Death Penalty Abolition Bills (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 17)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly Materials (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 18)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly Moratorium (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 19)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB1554 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 20)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB1922 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 21)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB1923 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 22)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB2517 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 23)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB2012 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 24)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB2657 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 25)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB2662 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 26)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly HB2787 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 27)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB141 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 28)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB705 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 29)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB7091 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 30)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB863 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 31)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB1143 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 32)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB1239 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 33)
  - 2003 Virginia General Assembly SB1241 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 34)
  - 2004 Bills VADP Supports 2004 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 35)
  - 2004 Juvenile Death Penalty Bill (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 36)
  - 2004 Legislative Information (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 37)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 38)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 39)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly Bill Tracking (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 40)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly Bill VADP Position (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 41)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly Calendar (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 42)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly Half Way Report (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 43)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly HB129 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 44)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly HB134 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 45)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly HB1341 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 46)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly HB1341 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 47)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly HB 1341 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 48)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB47, Undated (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 49)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB117 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 50)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB177 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 51)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB218 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 52)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB271 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 53)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB319 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 54)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB330 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 55)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB333 - Writ of Innocence, Undated (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 56)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB609 - Final Judgment (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 57)
  - 2004 Virginia General Assembly SB1341 - Juvenile Death Penalty (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 58)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 59)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly Dates (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 60)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB1800 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 61)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB1812 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 62)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB1879 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 63)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB1976 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 64)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB1879 - Abolish Death Penalty For Class 1 Felonies (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 65)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB2216 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 66)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB2306 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 67)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB2663 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 68)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly HB2773 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 69)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly SB318 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 70)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly SB808 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 71)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly SB914 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 72)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly SB915 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 73)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly HB1018 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 74)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly SB1177 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 75)
  - 2005 Virginia General Assembly Juvenile Death Penalty (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 76)
  - 2006 Senate and House Bill Tally (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 77)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly Bills VADP Supports (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 78)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly HB188 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 79)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly HB782 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 80)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly HB1311 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 81)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly SB362 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 82)
  - 2007 Virginia General Assembly, Undated (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 83)
  - 2007 Virginia General Assembly Bills VADP Supports (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 84)
  - 2006 Virginia General Assembly HB45 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 85)
  - 2007 Virginia General Assembly SB1288 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 86)
  - 2007 Virginia General Assembly SB1295 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 87)
  - ABA Comprehensive Review of Indigent Defense in Virginia, 2004 (Box 1 (2-Legal), Folder 88)
  - ABA Guidelines for Death Penalty Attorneys, 2003 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 1)
  - ABA Juvenile Death Penalty Representation, 2002 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 2)
  - Abolition of Death Penalty in Europe, 2004 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 3)
  - An Act to Amend the Code of Virginia, 2004-2005 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 4)
  - Angel Breard Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus, Undated (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 5)
  - Ann Meng Testimony on SB914, 2005; Undated (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 6)
  - Barnes v. Thompson, 1995 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 7)
  - Bennett v. Angelone, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 8)
  - Anthony Porter, Undated (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 9)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 10, 1997 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 10)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 11, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 11)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 12, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 12)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 12, 2000 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 13)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 13, 2000 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 14)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 13, 2001 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 15)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 14, 2001 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 16)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 14, 2002 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 17)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 15, 2002 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 18)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 15, 2003 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 19)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 16, 2003 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 20)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 16, 2004 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 21)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 17, 2004 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 22)
  - Capital Defense Journal Vol. 17, 2005 (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 23)
  - Clarence Hill, 2007; Undated (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 24)
  - Clark v. Townley, Undated (Box 2 (2-Legal), Folder 25)
  - Continuing Legal Education: Avoiding Death by Avoiding Trial, 2003 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 1)
  - Continuing Legal Education: Emerging Issues in Capital Cases (1 of 2), 2004 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 2)
  - Continuing Legal Education: Emerging Issues in Capital Cases (2 of 2), 2004 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 3)
  - Continuing Legal Education: The Capital Jury, 2001 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 4)
  - Correll v. Thompson Appeal, 1995 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 5)
  - Death Penalty in other States, 1988 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 6)
  - Edmunds v. Thomson, 1990 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 7)
  - Execution of Mentally Retarded Persons, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 8)
  - FBI Facsimile Coversheet, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 9)
  - Gary Beeman, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 10)
  - Giarratano v. Warden Thompson, 1987 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 11)
  - G Ray v. Netherland, 1996 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 12)
  - Harold Wilson, 2005 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 13)
  - Harold Wilson, 2006 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 14)
  - Hendrick v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 15)
  - Huke v. Netherland, 1996 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 16)
  - Jenkins v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1992 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 17)
  - Jerry Conner, 2006 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 18)
  - John Ballard, 2006; Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 19)
  - Joseph v. Angelone, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 20)
  - Juvenile Death Penalty Legislation from Other States, 2002; 2004; Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 21)
  - Key Legislators in Virginia, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 22)
  - Lee v. Taylor, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 23)
  - Life Without Parole and the End of Future Dangerousness, 2005 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 24)
  - Lobbying Against the Death Penalty, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 25)
  - Loyola of Los Angeles Las Review, 1989 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 26)
  - Mackall v. Angelone, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 27)
  - Quesinberry v. Taylor, 1998 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 28)
  - Mickens v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1994 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 29)
  - Mitigating Evidence Guidelines, 1990 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 30)
  - Nick Yarris, 2006 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 31)
  - Paul House, 2006 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 32)
  - Perry v. Texas, 1985 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 33)
  - Racial Justice Act Materials, 1989-1990 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 34)
  - Review of Virginia's System of Capital Punishment, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 35)
  - Roger Keith Coleman an Innocent Man on Death Row, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 36)
  - Satcher v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1992 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 37)
  - SB333 Fact Sheet, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 38)
  - Section 1912 Juvenile Death Penalty, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 39)
  - Senate and House Districts, 2004 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 40)
  - Sheppard v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1995 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 41)
  - Slezak v. Evatt, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 42)
  - Smith v. Angelone, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 43)
  - Smith v. Murray, 1986 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 44)
  - Stanley "Tookie" Williams, 2006 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 45)
  - State Capital Representation, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 46)
  - Stickler v. Greene, 1998 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 47)
  - Stout v. Thompson, 1995 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 48)
  - Streamlined Procedures ACT, 2005 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 49)
  - Study of Virginia General Assembly Bills, 2003 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 50)
  - Texas Fair Defense Act, 2003 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 51)
  - VADP Amicus Brief, 2004; Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 52)
  - Vernon Evans, 2006 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 53)
  - Virginia Code 21 Day Rule, 2004 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 54)
  - Virginia Department of Corrections Audit, 2003 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 55)
  - Virginia General Assembly, 1988-1990 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 56)
  - Virginia General Assembly Death Penalty Bills, 1999; 2002 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 57)
  - Virginia General Assembly Materials, 1984; 1989-1991; Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 58)
  - Virginia House Members, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 59)
  - Weeks v. Angelone, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 60)
  - William Saunders for Execution Clemency, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 61)
  - Williams v. Pruett, Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 62)
  - Williams v. Taylor, 1999; Undated (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 63)
  - Wright v. Angelone, 1998 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 64)
  - Wright v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1993 (Box 3 (2-Legal), Folder 65)
- Publications, 1975-2008; 3; 2.6 cubic ft.
  Publications include newsletters, magazines, and studies that Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty use to support ongoing efforts to abolish capital punishment. Flyers and pamphlets are also included in this series.
  - 100 Innocents Released from Death Row, 2002 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 1)
  - 1996 DPIC Report (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 2)
  - 1997 Death Penalty Year end Review (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 3)
  - 2000 Death Penalty Year End Report (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 4)